瓦雷利亚末日
伊耿一世（AC1-37 在位）
“征服者”
镶嵌红宝石的瓦雷利亚钢王冠
坦格利安家族征服维斯特洛
雷妮丝
伊耿一世的妹妹和妻子
伊尼斯一世（AC37-42 在位）
镶嵌翡翠和珍珠的黄金王冠
杰赫里斯一世（AC48-103 在位）
“和解者”“人瑞王”
镶嵌翡翠和珍珠的黄金王冠
杰赫里斯一世（AC48-103 在位）
“和解者”“人瑞王”
镶嵌翡翠和珍珠的黄金王冠
亚莉珊（AC36-100）
“善良王后”
杰赫里斯一世的妹妹和妻子
贝尔隆（AC57-101）
“勇敢的”“春晓王子”
杰赫里斯一世的儿子和国王之手
阿莱莎（AC60-84）
贝尔隆的妹妹和妻子
戴蒙
“浪荡王子”
贝尔隆的儿子 韦赛里斯一世的弟弟
戴蒙
“浪荡王子”
贝尔隆的儿子 韦赛里斯一世的弟弟
兰娜尔·瓦列利安
科利斯和雷妮丝的女儿 戴蒙的妻子
贝妮拉·坦格利安
戴蒙与兰娜尔的长女
雷妮亚·坦格利安
戴蒙与兰娜尔的次女
雷妮拉
韦赛里斯一世的女儿和王储
瓦列利安家族参加王室婚礼
改编自 《血与火：坦格利安王朝史》
[美] 乔治·马丁 著
龙 王 家 族
第一季 第八集
潮汛之主 The Lord of the Tides
距离上次见到我的夫君大人已经六年了 学士
It's been near six years since I last saw my lord husband, Maester.
我必须得知道……他能活下来吗？
I must know... will he live?
他带领船员们冲上一艘伪装过的破船
He led his sailors into an ambush.
结果中了埋伏
A ship made to look as if it were abandoned.
在战斗中 他被海盗用匕首划伤了脖子
In the fighting, his neck was slashed by a corsair's dagger.
掉进了海里
He fell overboard into the sea.
伤势很重
The wound was severe.
流了很多血
Much blood was lost.
但更令人担忧的是随之而来的高烧
But the greater concern is the fever that followed.
雷妮丝·坦格利安
“无冕女王” 韦赛里斯一世的堂姐 科利斯的妻子
随船学士说他是从身体内部烧起来的
The ship's maester said he burns from within.
贝妮拉·坦格利安
戴蒙与兰娜尔的长女
渡鸦是从哪来的？
The ravens came in from?
暮临厅 公主殿下
Evenfall, Princess.
暮临厅地处风暴地的塔斯岛上，位于风息堡以东，在龙石岛和潮头岛的南方
看来他们会在三天后抵达
So they arrive in three days.
魏蒙德·瓦列利安
科利斯的弟弟
做好一切准备等他回来 凯尔温学士
Let all be made ready to receive him, Maester Kelvyn.
海蛇向来强壮
The Sea Snake is strong.
毫无疑问
No doubt.
但有些死于血热病人 年纪只有他一半 我就见过
And yet, I have seen blood fever overcome men half his age.
不要在我们家乌鸦嘴 魏蒙德
I will not suffer the talk of crows in my house, Vaemond.
我爱我哥哥……
I love my brother...
但我们必须面对现实
but we must be honest with ourselves.
等我们接到船 他可能已经不在了
We may greet his ship to find him gone.
那由谁来坐上浮木王座呢？
And who will take the Driftwood Throne?
我外婆正坐得很舒服呢
My grandmother seems quite comfortable here.
只有她丈夫不在的时候 她才能代行职责
She presides only in the absence of her husband.
如果我哥哥死了 这个位置就该传下去
On his death, the seat passes.
传给路斯里斯·瓦列利安
To Lucerys Velaryon.
正如我夫君大人所愿
As is my lord husband's desire.
我和海蛇血脉同源
I am the Sea Snake's own blood,
我是他在世上最亲的家人
the closest kin he has left.
注意你的发言 小叔
Be careful, good-brother.
要是被人听到 可是叛国之罪
One could take your words for treason.
我只是说句实话 雷妮丝
I speak the truth, Rhaenys.
而且你心里有数
And you know it.
此事已决
The matter has been decided.
可正是做出这个决定的人
By a man whose ambition
他的野心给我们家族带来了一次又一次的灾难
has brought down on us calamity after calamity.
我哥哥只在意史书怎么记载
My brother cares only for the history books.
但瓦列利安家族的血脉呢？
But what of the Velaryon line?
就该这样断绝吗
Is it to be snuffed out,
就该被斯壮家的狗崽子们取代吗？
supplanted by the pups of House Strong?
潮头岛于情于理都应归我所有
Driftmark is mine by all rights.
有你支持固然很好
And while I should like your support,
但我其实并不……需要
I do not... need it.
风向已经变了
The winds have shifted.
朝廷有充分的理由支持我
The crown has good reason to take my side.
我的国王堂弟会为这个拔了你的舌头
My cousin the King would have your tongue for this.
但而今坐在铁王座上的已经不是国王了 嫂子
But it's not a king who sits the Iron Throne these days, good-sister.
是王后
It's a queen.
戴蒙·坦格利安
“浪荡王子” 韦赛里斯的弟弟
叙拉克斯新下了一窝蛋
Syraks drōmuni arliar mādas.
有三颗
Hāriar drōma.
三颗!
Hāriar drōma!
把它们放到保温室里
Dijemiot hannēliks lōtūljās.
马上就去 王子殿下
Sīrgō, dārilaros ñuhys.
学士带来了这个
Maester kesi mādas.
刚收到 来自潮头岛的贝妮拉小姐
Sīr amastas, hen Driftmākot Ābrāzmā Baelā.
父亲，向您禀报魏蒙德叔叔的最新动向，此刻他正驶向君临，
将要面见国王陛下，奏请继承、权利以及神圣血脉等相关事宜。
他称自己为浮木王座唯一完美的继承人选，并请求陛下恩准，依法继承。
——贝妮拉
雷妮拉·坦格利安
“王国之光” 龙石岛公主 王储
征服者和他的姐妹率领一支强大的军队航行
The Conqueror and his sisters sailed with a great army.
Se Blākuata Rāsho drāñot vilinio viārtis.
并在黑水河登陆
And landed at the Blackwater Rush.
Drāñot.
Drāñot. Drāñot.
杰卡里斯·瓦列利安
雷妮拉与兰尼诺的长子
Drāñot 是“在末端”？
Drāñot. At the end?
是河口
The mouth.
河口！加油啊 小杰 你明明知道的
Mouth! Come on, Jace, you knew that.
Drāñot. Drāñot.
在河口登陆
Drāñot vilinio viārtis.
Drāñot.
Drāñot 加油啊 小杰
Drāñot. Come on, Jace.
我看今天早上就到这吧
Perhaps that's enough for this morning.
不 不 我想继续
No, no. I want to keep going.
学士
Maester.
Guēsi misenakson Aegon ūndas.
伊耿……下令将树……
Aegon... ordered that the trees should be...
……杀掉
...killed.
砍掉
Felled.
这两个词有关联
It is a related word.
“misēnakson”意为“被砍倒”；“sēnakson”意为“被杀死”
我没打算让你一天就学会高等瓦雷利亚语 小杰
I don't expect you to learn High Valyrian in a day, Jace.
国王应当以祖先的传统为荣
A king should honor the traditions of his forbears.
不过……除非你正打算要废黜自己的母亲
Well... unless you're planning to depose your own mother,
否则你学习的时间还多着呢
you have plenty of time to study.
退下吧
Leave us.
乔佛里……来
Joffrey... come.
乔佛里·瓦列利安
雷妮拉与兰尼诺的三子
他是在质疑小路的合法身份
He means to call into question Luke's legitimacy.
进而质疑小杰
And by extension Jace,
最终质疑我对铁王座的继承权
and by extension my own claim to the throne.
魏蒙德只关心潮头岛和瓦列利安的血脉
Vaemond cares only about Driftmark and the Velaryon line.
不关心我们的政治
Not about our politics.
他和奥托·海塔尔达成共识了吗？
Has he made common cause with Otto Hightower yet?
我就担心这个
This is what I fear.
雷妮丝已经飞去宫里了
Rhaenys has flown to court.
当然 她不可能支持他
Surely, she cannot be planning to back him.
不会的 无论我们之间有什么分歧
No. Whatever disagreements we may have had,
她不会那么残忍……
she's not cruel...
- 也不会蠢到那么做 - 分歧？
-or stupid enough to do that. -Disagreements?
她认定我们为了结婚害死了她的儿子
She believes we had her son killed so that we might marry.
是的……但她仍然亲手养大了贝妮拉
Yes... and yet, she's taken Baela to ward.
对 但这是为了兰娜尔 她对咱俩没感情
Yes. It is Laena's memory she honors. She has no love for us.
毒蛇的毒液已经蔓延这么远了吗？
Has the vipers' venom spread so far?
那些毒蛇正以我父亲的名义统治国家
Those vipers rule in my father's name.
而我父亲——
And my father--
我还有什么选择的余地？
What choice do I have?
那就去君临吧
To King's Landing, then.
欢迎坦格利安家族的雷妮拉
All hail Rhaenyra of House Targaryen,
龙石岛公主 铁王座继承人
Princess of Dragonstone and heir to the Iron Throne
以及他的王夫 戴蒙·坦格利安王子
and her royal consort, Prince Daemon Targaryen.
阿伦·卡斯威
欢迎回家 公主殿下
Welcome back, Princess.
卡斯威大人
Lord Caswell.
我本想说回家真好 但我几乎认不出这里了
I would say it's nice to be home, but I scarcely recognize it.
自打石阶列岛的问题解决以来
We have continued to enjoy improved customs duties
我们从增长的关税中持续获益
since the settling of the Stepstones.
至于我们能加以利用的份额
And the extent to which we exploit those
阿莉森·海塔尔
摄政王后 奥托之女
取决于港口总管的收入
is contingent on the harbor master's receipts.
关于这个事 呃 那个 修士们再度请求
Of which, um, uh, the, uh, septons have requested
林曼·毕斯柏里
财政大臣
奥托·海塔尔
王后的父亲 国王之手
从中拿出一半
half that again for a bronze bust
欧维尔
大学士
贾斯皮·威尔德
法务大臣
为圣母节定……定制一座青铜半身像
they wish to co--commission for the, the Festival of the Mother,
泰兰·兰尼斯特
凯岩城公爵杰森的双胞胎弟弟 海政大臣
那个 我并不建议批准
which I would not recommend.
谢谢您的详尽说明 毕斯柏里大人
Thank you for that exhaustive accounting, Lord Beesbury.
我提醒您——
I remind you--
哈罗德·维斯特林
御林铁卫队长
您的客人到了 陛下
Your guests have arrived, Your Grace.
依照您的指示 我相信他们得到了
I trust they've been welcomed as befits their station.
和身份相称的接待 首相大人
As you instructed, Lord Hand.
据我所知 科利斯大人希望他的孙子路斯里斯
It was my understanding Lord Corlys wished for his grandson Lucerys
继承潮汛之主的头衔
to succeed him as Lord of the Tides.
那孩子长到现在 一多半时间都离潮头岛很远
The boy has been raised most of his life away from Driftmark.
确实 他能驾驭龙 但他能指挥舰队吗？
He can fly a dragon, yes, but can he command a fleet?
能力不影响他的继承权
Ability does not alter his claim.
海蛇从未为了以防万一
The Sea Snake has never formally named him as heir,
而正式确定继承人
if it comes to that.
朝廷必须做出对国家最好的选择
The crown must choose what is best for the realm.
他可是兰尼诺的儿子 有什么根据——
He is Laenor's son. What grounds could there be--
就是有什么 毕斯柏里大人
What indeed, Lord Beesbury.
就是有什么
What indeed.
明日 我们将听取雷妮拉公主
We shall hear Princess Rhaenyra's petition,
以及其他诉求者的陈情
along with those of the other claimants on the morrow.
- 但—— - 请见谅 各位大人
-But-- -I do beg your pardon, my lords.
我得去和客人们打个招呼
I must greet our guests.
我们要对出售新羊毛征税吗？
Shall we levy a tax on the sale of new wool?
陛下……
Your Grace...
有件事情劳您分神
a matter has arisen that requires your attention.
亚历克爵士 无论是什么 都得等等再说
Whatever it is, Ser Arryk, it'll need to wait.
- 我是伊利克 陛下 - 当然 抱歉 爵士
-I'm Erryk, Your Grace. -Of course. My apologies, ser.
是王子的事
It's about the Prince.
他房里的突发状况 非常棘手
There's been a delicate situation in his apartments.
父亲？
Father?
韦赛里斯·坦格利安一世
国王
- 什么人？ - 父亲
-Who goes there? -Father.
是我 国王陛下
It's me, my King.
雷妮拉
Rhaenyra.
噢……
Oh...
我和戴蒙来了
I'm here with Daemon.
戴蒙？
Daemon?
戴蒙
Daemon.
扶我起来
Help me up.
喔……
Oh...
好久不见了
It has been so long.
海蛇在石阶列岛打仗 受了重伤
The Sea Snake has taken a grave wound in battle in the Stepstones.
什么时候？
When?
我们好多年前就赢了啊
We won that war years ago.
不
No.
三城同盟会又回来了
The Triarchy is resurgent.
又打起来了
The fighting is anew.
而且有人——
And there is a p--
有人陈情 要求裁定潮头岛继承权
There is a petition to decide upon the succession of Driftmark
以及浮木王座的继承人
and the heir to the Driftwood Throne.
陈情？
Petitions?
阿莉森和奥托……现在是他们说了算
Alicent and Otto... they see to all that business now.
不 哥哥 听我说
No, brother, listen to me.
你要声明你的立场
You are to affirm your position for Lucerys
让路斯里斯成为科利斯·瓦列利安的继承人
to be Corlys Velaryon's successor.
科利斯伯爵出什么事了吗？
Has something happened to Lord Corlys?
父亲……
Father...
有两个人 我们想让您见见
there's someone we wish to introduce you to.
戴蒙
Daemon.
哥哥
Brother.
那是谁？
Who is that?
父亲……
Father...
这是伊耿
this is Aegon.
伊耿
Aegon.
这是……韦塞里斯
And this... is Viserys.
啊……韦塞里斯
Ah... Viserys.
这个名字很有王者风范
Now that is a name fit for a king.
哦……
Oh...
哦 哦……
Oh, oh...
哦 抱歉
Oh, I'm sorry.
哦 抱歉 抱歉
Oh, I'm sorry. I'm sorry.
抱——
I'm so--
抱歉 我——
I'm sorry. I'm sor--
帮我一下
Please.
我的茶 茶
My tea. My tea.
什么茶？这杯吗？
What tea? This?
对 对
Yes. Yes.
是的
Yes.
我第一时间把她带来了
I brought her here immediately.
没人看见 王后陛下
She's seen no one else, Your Grace.
塔雅
王后的侍女
过来 亲爱的
Come here, sweetling.
告诉我你的名字
Tell me your name.
我叫黛安娜 王后陛下
It's Dyana, Your Grace.
希望您喜欢这名字
If it please you.
黛安娜 多美的名字
Dyana. What a pretty name.
我明白你遇到麻烦了
I understand you've found yourself in some trouble.
我当时在给王子送酒
I was fetching the Prince his wine,
我把酒放在他的桌子上 当我转身时——
and I put it on his table, and when I turned--
我没看见他
I didn't see him.
我请求他停下 陛下
I asked him to stop, Your Grace.
我真的求了……
I did, truly...
您一定要相信我
you must believe me.
谢谢你告诉我 黛安娜
Thank you for telling me, Dyana.
- 我知道这不是你的过错 - 嗯？
-I know it wasn't your fault. -Hm?
我相信你
I believe you.
真——真的吗？
Y-You do?
是的
I do.
但我担心的是……
But what I worry about...
其他人是否会相信
is what others might believe.
你当时和王子独处一室 是吗？
You were alone with the Prince, were you not?
是的 我——
Yes, I--
没人看见你们俩之间发生了什么
And no one else saw what happened between the two of you.
如果其他人听说这件事——
If anyone else were to hear about this--
- 我没有跟任何人说 - 你告诉了伊利克爵士 塔雅还有我
-I haven't told anyone. -You told Ser Erryk and Talya and now me.
虽然我相信不是你的错 但其他人可能不会那么相信
And though I believe you are not to blame, others might not be so trusting.
他们可能认为你是想败坏王子的名声 或者更糟的是……
They might think you were trying to besmirch the Prince, or worse...
从一开始就是你勾引了他
that you're the sort of girl that might have enticed him in the first place.
你知道这样的女孩会有怎样的下场
And you know what happens to girls like that.
我一定守口如瓶只字不提 陛下
I wouldn't dream of breathing another word to anyone, Your Grace.
我以性命发誓
I swear it on my life.
我知道你不会说的
I know you won't.
一点补偿
For your troubles.
茶来了 陛下
The tea, Your Grace.
最好万无一失
It's best to be certain.
起床
Get up.
伊耿！
Aegon!
起床！
Get up!
伊耿·坦格利安
“大伊耿” 韦赛里斯与阿莉森的长子
母亲？
Mother?
什么事？
What is it?
“什么事？什么事？”
"What is it? What is it?"
“什么事？”你就只会说这一句话？
"What is it?" That's all you can say for yourself?
发生什么事了吗？
Has something happened?
黛安娜
Dyana.
那个侍女
The serving girl.
哦 看在诸神的份上
Oh, for the gods' sake.
那个女孩 伊耿 从你身边跑掉的
The girl, Aegon. The one you sent fleeing from your company.
哦 就是找个乐子
Oh, it was just harmless fun.
没什么大不了 她犯不着生气
She didn't need to go and get upset about it.
想想这给你的妻子和我带来的耻辱
Think of the shame on your wife, on me.
你怎么能一直这样
How can you keep carrying on like this,
尤其是在今天这样的日子？
especially on a day like today?
怎么了？今天是什么日子？
Why? What is it today?
我没你这个儿子
You are no son of mine.
我也没求着当啊
I did not ask for this.
我做了你要求我做的一切
I've done everything you've asked me to,
我这样……
and I try so...
我这样努力 但是你和父亲从不满意
I try so hard, but it will never be enough for you or father.
你看见黛安娜了吗？ 她本该给孩子们穿衣服的
Have you seen Dyana? She's supposed to dress the children.
他看起来像是变了一个人
He looks like a different person.
我认为我们应该再咨询一下格拉底斯学士
I believe we should also consult Maester Gerardys.
如果他能看看国王 也许会给点不同的建议——
Perhaps if he could see the King, he'd suggest a different--
雷妮拉公主
Princess Rhaenyra.
戴蒙王子
And Prince Daemon.
好久不见 大驾光临 我们万分荣幸
It has been so long since we were granted the joy of your presence.
的确如此 王后陛下
Indeed, Your Grace.
但也没久到值得隆重欢迎的程度
Though not long enough to merit a greeting upon our arrival.
我敢肯定王后有要务在身 亲爱的
I'm sure the Queen had pressing business, my love.
治理国家的事 我们俩又懂什么呢？
What can either of us know of ruling a kingdom?
你们很清楚 不是我在治理
I do not rule, as you well know.
我和我父亲只不过是服务于国王的意志和智慧
My father and I are mere stewards of the King's will and wisdom.
那么国王陛下到底是如何表达智慧的？
And how exactly is that wisdom expressed?
通过眨眼和喘气吗？
In blinks and wheezes?
他要是还能记住自己的名字 我都要大吃一惊
I'd be surprised if he could remember his own name.
- 要是你能记住也行 - 自从上次会面之后
-Or if you could. -King Viserys's condition
韦塞里斯陛下的状况日渐恶化
has worsened since you saw him last.
这使他遭受巨大痛苦
It subjects him to considerable pain.
- 按照学士们的建议—— - 啊 学士们
-On the advice of the maesters-- -Ah, the maesters.
当然 就是他们让他……
Of course. It is they who keep him...
迷上了罂粟花奶 好叫海塔尔们帮他暖王座
addled on milk of the poppy while the Hightowers warm his throne.
雷妮拉 你是没见过他离开罂粟花奶 痛到不省人事的样子
Rhaenyra, if you would see him without it, almost blind with suffering.
阿莉森 我毫不怀疑 你这样做纯粹是出于仁慈
Alicent, I have no doubt it was an act of the purest mercy,
不过告诉我 如果是为了减轻国王的痛苦
but tell me, for the King's suffering,
学士们难道也开了方子 要求去掉坦格利安纹章
did the maesters also prescribe the removal of Targaryen heraldry
换上各种雕像和七芒星图案？
and the installation in its stead of various statues and stars?
七神徽章只是为了在未知的道路上引领我们
The emblems of the Seven serve only to guide us on an uncertain path.
- 提醒我们世间还有更高的权威 - 那么明天
-To remind us of a higher authority. -And on the morrow,
又是哪位权威将会裁断我儿子对自己遗产的所有权？
which authority will sit in judgment of my son's claim on his own inheritance?
会是我……和国王之手
That would be mine... and the Hand's.
但请放心 天父是公正的
But be assured, the Father is just and commands me
他命令我忘记你今天在这间屋子里提出的控诉
to forget the accusations you have hurled in this room today.
路斯里斯·瓦列利安
雷妮拉与兰尼诺的次子
- 比我记忆中要小 - 和我记忆中完全一样
-Smaller than I remember. -It looks exactly the same.
小路 快来
Luke, come on.
看见了吗？我就说肯定还在
See? I told you this would still be here.
那时候你以为能挥动克里斯顿的流星锤
And you thought you could swing Criston's morningstar.
结果差点搞得脑袋搬家
And you almost took your own head off.
- 你怎么了？- 人人都在盯着我们
-What's your problem? -Everyone's staring at us.
没有人会质疑我是潮头岛的继承人……
No one would question me being heir to Driftmark...
假如……
if...
假如我看起来更像兰尼诺·瓦列利安爵士 而不是哈尔温·斯壮爵士
if I looked more like Ser Laenor Velaryon than Ser Harwin Strong.
他们的想法并不重要
It doesn't matter what they think.
克里斯顿·科尔
御林铁卫
伊蒙德·坦格利安
韦赛里斯与阿莉森的次子
干得好 王子
Well done, my Prince.
你很快就会在比武大会上获胜
You'll be winning tourneys in no time.
我才不在乎比武大会
I don't give a shit about tourneys.
两位外甥……
Nephews...
你们是来训练的吗？
have you come to train?
开门！
Open the gate!
保持镇定 王后陛下
Hold your nerve, my Queen.
我们所做的一切都是为了王国的利益
What we do, we do for the good of the realm.
必须承认 眼下这事让我非常不安
I must confess a certain uneasiness now this is at hand.
- 他可能还活着 - 但如果他已经不在了 我们必须有所准备
-He may yet live. -But we must be prepared if he does not.
归功于杰赫里斯和韦塞里斯的治理
The realm has enjoyed a long peace,
王国已经享有很长一段时间的安定和平
a credit to the work of both Jaehaerys and Viserys,
但战争的威胁迫在眉睫 随时会抵达我们的海岸
but the threat of war looms and may arrive on our shores.
如果战争真的来了 你会想要一个孩子来指挥
When it does, will you want a child at the command
维斯特洛最强大的舰队吗？
of the greatest fleet in Westeros?
当然了 我们的所作所为
We must, of course...
必须以臣民利益为重
act in the interest of our subjects.
王后陛下 下一任潮汐之主会知恩图报的
The next Lord of the Tides will be deeply in your debt, Your Grace.
潮头岛也一样会……
As will Driftmark...
全力以赴
in all its strength.
外婆？
Grandmother?
雷妮亚
Rhaena.
雷妮亚·坦格利安
戴蒙与兰娜尔的次女
贝妮拉说你可能在这里
Baela said you might be here.
你把她照顾得很好
She's done well as your ward.
你……
You've...um...
把她养育得出类拔萃
raised her admirably.
过奖了 公主
You honor me, Princess.
我能和公主单独聊几句吗 雷妮亚？
Might I speak to the Princess alone, Rhaena?
先告退了 公主
Princess.
我想了很久 你来这儿的目的是什么
I wondered for many an hour what your purpose was in coming here.
关于魏蒙德爵士的控诉 你到底是站在哪边
Whether you'd speak for or against the suit brought by Ser Vaemond.
但是后来我意识到
But then, I realized...
你是站在自己这边
you intend to advocate for yourself.
这次议程是不公平的
This is no fair proceeding.
我打赌这是王后和首相设下的圈套
It is a trap set by the Queen and the Hand, I'd wager,
他们想借此宣告我的儿子是私生子
to proclaim my son illegitimate.
但你对兰尼诺的所作所为更加恶劣
Yet you did worse than that with Laenor.
不是吗?
Did you not?
我爱你的儿子
I loved your son.
你可能不相信 但我真的爱他
You may not believe it to be true, but I did.
我没有派人杀他
I did not order his death.
也没有参与谋划 我可以发誓
Nor was I complicit in it. I swear this to you.
我有个提议
I'll make you an offer.
你支持小路的继承权
Back Luke's claim,
同时让兰娜尔的两个女儿和我的两个儿子订婚
and let us betroth Laena's children to mine.
贝妮拉将会成为七大王国的王后
Baela will be Queen of the Seven Kingdoms
她的子嗣将会成为铁王座的继承人
and her sons will be heirs to the throne.
雷妮亚将统治潮头岛
Rhaena will rule in Driftmark, and
以后再由她和路斯里斯的孩子继承爵位
the seat will pass to her and Lucerys's children in time.
慷慨的提议
A generous offer.
- 或者说是绝望的提议  - 重要吗?
-Or a desperate one. -What does it matter?
确实不重要
You are right in this, at least.
至少你说对了这点
It does not matter.
随你怎么讨价还价
You can bargain with me all you like.
或是把孙女带过来想让我心软
Bring my granddaughter with you to soften my resolve.
但是明天 海塔尔家族会率先出击
But tomorrow, the Hightowers land their first blow.
他们会强迫你屈服
They force you to your knees...
而我必定会保持中立
and I must stand alone.
阿莉森?
Alicent?
阿莉森……
Alicent...
父亲 是我 雷妮拉
No, it's Rhaenyra, father.
雷妮拉
Rhaenyra.
冰与火之歌 您相信它会成真吗?
"The Song of Ice and Fire." Do you believe it to be true?
伊耿的梦
Aegon's Dream.
是您告诉我
You told me
团结整个王国 对抗共同的敌人 是我们的职责
it was our duty to hold the realm united against a common foe.
您立我为继承人 却导致王国走向分裂
By naming me heir, you divided the realm.
我以为我想要铁王座
I thought I wanted it.
但这负担太重了
But the burden is a heavy one.
真的太重了
It's too heavy.
我……
My...
我唯一的孩子
My only child.
如果您想要我担起重任 那就支持我
If you wish me to bear it, then defend me.
和我的孩子们
And my children.
这……
It's...
给我准备晚餐 奥托
I want to have supper, Otto.
- 现在是早上了 陛下  - 今晚
-It is the morning, Your Grace. -Tonight.
我所有的家人
The whole of my family
都在红堡团聚
are gathered at the Red Keep.
我希望……我们能一起吃顿饭
I want us... to dine together.
把罂粟花奶拿过来
Bring milk of the poppy.
不要
No.
安排晚餐就好
Just arrange the supper.
朝廷非常希望
Though it is the great hope of this court
科利斯·瓦列利安大人能够平安归来
that Lord Corlys Velaryon survive his wounds,
但我们聚集在此 有着更加沉重的任务
we gather here with the grim task
那就是解决潮头岛的继承人问题
of dealing with the succession of Driftmark.
作为首相 我代表国王就此事
As Hand, I speak with the King's voice on this
和其他所有问题发言
and all other matters.
朝廷现在开始听取陈情
The crown will now hear the petitions.
海伦娜·坦格利安
韦赛里斯与阿莉森的女儿
瓦列利安家族的魏蒙德爵士
Ser Vaemond of House Velaryon.
王后陛下
My Queen.
首相大人
My Lord Hand.
我们家族的历史可以从七大王国
The history of our noble houses extends beyond the Seven Kingdoms
一直追溯到古瓦雷利亚时代
to the days of Old Valyria.
坦格利安家族一直统治着天空
For as long as House Targaryen has ruled the skies,
正如瓦列利安家族统治着海洋
House Velaryon has ruled the seas.
瓦雷利亚末日浩劫之后 我们两个家族成为最后的幸存者
When the Doom fell on Valyria, our houses became the last of their kind.
我们的祖先来到这片全新的土地 他们知道如果失败
Our forebearers came to this new land, knowing that were they to fail,
将意味着血脉和姓氏的终结
it would mean the end to their bloodlines and their name.
我这辈子 都在潮头岛坚定捍卫哥哥的统治
I have spent my entire life on Driftmark defending my brother's seat.
我是科利斯大人的至亲 我们血脉同源
I am Lord Corlys's closest kin, his own blood.
我的血管里流淌着真正的 不容置疑的瓦列利安之血
The true, unimpeachable blood of House Velaryon runs through my veins.
我的儿子们也是如此 他们是兰尼诺·瓦列利安的孩子
As it does in my sons, the offspring of Laenor Velaryon.
如果你真的在意家族血脉 魏蒙德爵士
If you cared so much about your house's blood, Ser Vaemond,
你就不该如此大胆 妄图取代家族的合法继承人
you would not be so bold as to supplant its rightful heir.
你的说辞不过是为了个人利益和野心
No, you only speak for yourself and for your own ambition.
稍候会有机会让你表达诉求 雷妮拉公主
You will have chance to make your own petition, Princess Rhaenyra.
请尊重魏蒙德爵士 听完他的发言
Do Ser Vaemond the courtesy of allowing his to be heard.
公主 你对瓦列利安的血脉了解多少?
What do you know of Velaryon blood, Princess?
就算我割开血管让你看看
I could cut my veins and show it to you
你也认不出来
and you still wouldn't recognize it.
此事关乎我们家族的未来和存亡 与你无关
This is about the future and survival of my house, not yours.
王后陛下 首相大人
My Queen, my Lord Hand.
这是血脉传承的问题 无关野心
This is a matter of blood, not ambition.
我把家族存亡和血脉延续置于一切之上
I place the continuation of the survival of my house and my line above all.
我谦卑地向各位提名自己
I humbly put myself before you as my brother's successor...
作为我的兄长 潮头岛伯爵 潮汛之主的继承人
the Lord of Driftmark and Lord of the Tides.
感谢你的发言 魏蒙德爵士
Thank you, Ser Vaemond.
雷妮拉公主 现在可以为你的儿子路斯里斯·瓦列利安发言了
Princess Rhaenyra, you may now speak for your son, Lucerys Velaryon.
如果面对这场闹剧 我还非得说点什么
If I am to grace this farce with some answer,
那我首先要提醒各位 大约二十年前 就在这个——
I will start by reminding the court that nearly 20 years ago, in this very--
坦格利安家族的
King Viserys of House Targaryen,
韦赛里斯一世
the First of His Name,
安达尔人 洛伊拿人
King of the Andals, and the Rhoynar,
和先民的国王
and the First Men,
七国统治者暨全境守护者 驾到！
Lord of the Seven Kingdoms, and Protector of the Realm.
今天我来坐铁王座
I will sit the throne today.
陛下
Your Grace.
我没事 我没事
I will be fine. I will be fine.
我说了我没事
I said I'm fine.
- 啊……   - 来吧
-Ah... -Come on.
稳住
Steady.
我必须……承认……我很疑惑
I must... admit... my confusion.
我不理解
I do not understand
继承人早已定下 还要陈什么情
why petitions are being heard over a settled succession.
在场唯一……
The only one present...
真正了解科利斯大人意愿的人
who might offer keener insight into Lord Corlys's wishes
是雷妮丝公主
is the Princess Rhaenys.
确实如此 陛下
Indeed, Your Grace.
我丈夫一直都希望潮头岛
It was ever my husband's will that Driftmark
由兰尼诺爵士的
pass through Ser Laenor
亲生儿子继承……
to his trueborn son...
也就是路斯里斯·瓦列利安
Lucerys Velaryon.
他的想法从未改变
His mind never changed.
我对他的支持也从未改变
Nor did my support of him.
事实上 雷妮拉公主刚刚向我表达了她的意愿
As a matter of fact, the Princess Rhaenyra has just informed me of her desire
她希望她的儿子 小杰和小路
to marry her sons Jace and Luke
与科利斯大人的外孙女 贝妮拉和雷妮亚订下婚约
to Lord Corlys's granddaughters, Baela and Rhaena.
我真心实意赞同这门亲事
A proposal to which I heartily agree.
那……就这么定了
Well... the matter is settled.
我再重申一遍
Again.
确立瓦列利安家族的路斯里斯王子
I hereby reaffirm Prince Lucerys of House Velaryon
为潮头岛和浮木王座的继承人
as heir to Driftmark,
暨下一任潮汛之主
the Driftwood Throne, and the next Lord of the Tides.
你违反了法律……
You break law...
破坏了延续几个世纪的传统
and centuries of tradition
让你的女儿做继承人
to install your daughter as heir.
但你休想告诉我……
Yet you dare tell me...
谁有资格做瓦列利安的继承人
who deserves to inherit the name Velaryon.
不行
No.
我决不允许
I will not allow it.
“允许”?
"Allow it"?
别忘了你的身份 魏蒙德
Do not forget yourself, Vaemond.
他不是真正的瓦列利安族人
That is no true Velaryon,
也绝对不是我的侄孙
and certainly no nephew of mine.
退下吧 你说得够多了
Go to your chambers. You have said enough.
路斯里斯是我的亲生外孙
Lucerys is my true-born grandson.
而你……
And you...
只不过是潮头岛的次子而已
are no more than the second son of Driftmark.
你……可以随意安排你的家族
You... may run your house as you see fit...
但是你不能决定我家族的未来
but you will not decide the future of mine.
我的家族从末日浩劫中幸存
My house survived the Doom
历经千百次磨难
and a thousand tribulations besides.
诸神见鬼去吧……
And gods be damned...
我绝不会看着我的家族灭亡于这个——
I will not see it ended on the account of this--
说出来
Say it.
她的孩子……
Her children...
是野种!
are bastards!
她……
And she...
是个……
is...
婊子
a whore.
我要……
I...
割了你的舌头
will have your tongue for that.
还是留着他的舌头吧
He can keep his tongue.
- 拿下他的武器！- 不必了
-Disarm him! -No need.
- 叫学士来！- 父亲？
-Call the maesters! -Father?
求你了亲爱的 你得喝点什么来止痛
Please, my love. You must take something for the pain.
我现在不能神智不清
I will not cloud my mind.
我得让事情回到正轨
I must put things right.
遗体明日即可启程送回潮头岛了 夫人
The body will be ready for its return to Driftmark on the morrow, my lady.
您可以让静默姐妹自己完成工作
You may wish to leave the Silent Sisters to their work.
直面死亡不大吉利
It is ill luck to look upon the face of death.
我已经数不清见过陌客多少次了 大学士
The Stranger has visited me more times than I can count, Grand Maester.
我敢说
I assure you...
他其实根本不在乎我是睁眼还是闭眼
he cares little whether my eyes are open or closed.
今晚见到你们……齐聚一堂……
How good it is... to see you all tonight...
我真高兴
together.
- 要餐前祈祷吗？ - 好
-Prayer before we begin? -Yes.
愿圣母慈爱的目光 欢笑着注视我们齐聚一堂
May the Mother smile down on this gathering with love.
愿铁匠修补我们断裂已久的纽带
May the Smith mend the bonds that have been broken for far too long.
至于魏蒙德·瓦列利安 愿诸神赐予他安息
And to Vaemond Velaryon, may the gods give him rest.
今天也是个值得庆祝的时刻
This is an occasion for celebration, it seems.
我的外孙们 小杰和小路
My grandsons, Jace and Luke,
会迎娶他们的表亲 贝妮拉与雷妮亚
will marry their cousins, Baela and Rhaena,
这使我们的家族血脉更加紧密相连
further strengthening the bond between our houses.
敬年轻的王子们……
A toast to the young Princes...
- 与他们的未婚妻 - 干杯 干杯！
-and their betrothed. -Hear, hear!
不错啊小杰 你终于能睡女人了
Well done, Jace. You'll finally get to lie with a woman.
让我们敬路斯里斯王子……
Let us toast as well Prince Lucerys...
未来的高潮城伯爵
the future Lord of the Tides.
干杯 干杯
Hear, hear.
你会成为大人物
You'll be great.
我猜 你知道那事儿该怎么干 对吧？
You do know how the act is done, I assume?
至少懂点儿理论吧？
At least in principle?
该把鸡巴放哪儿啊啥的
Where to put your cock and all that.
别理他 表哥
Let it be, cousin.
你要想扮演弄臣 那随意 但在我未婚妻面前最好管住你的嘴
You can play the jester if you wish, but hold your tongue before my betrothed.
我既是满心欢喜
It both gladdens my heart
又充满悲伤
and fills me with sorrow
只因见到你们齐聚于此
to see these faces around the table.
你们都是我在这个世界上最亲近的人……
The faces most dear to me in all the world...
但在过去的多年中 你们彼此却……
yet grown so distant from each other...
渐行渐远 充满隔阂
in the years past.
我这张脸……
My own face...
早已不复往昔的英俊……
is no longer a handsome one...
如果以前还算英俊的话
if indeed it ever was.
但是今晚……
But tonight...
我希望你们看到的是我……我本人
I wish you to see me... as I am.
不仅仅是君主……
Not just a king...
而是你们的父亲
but your father.
兄弟
Your brother.
丈夫……
Your husband...
和外公
and your grandsire.
一个 似乎……
Who may not, it seems...
已经行将就木的老人
walk for much longer among you.
让我们心中不要再充满恶意
Let us no longer hold ill feelings in our hearts.
若龙王家族内部分崩离析
The crown cannot stand strong
王权则难以稳固
if the House of the Dragon remains divided.
放下心中的不满吧
But set aside your grievances.
哪怕不是为了王权……
if not for the sake of the crown...
而是为了我这个
then for the sake of this old man
爱你们至深的
who loves you all
老人
so dearly.
我想举杯敬王后陛下
I wish to raise my cup to Her Grace, the Queen.
我爱我的父亲
I love my father.
但我得承认 没人能像……
But I must admit that no one has stood...
他身旁的妻子那样对他忠诚
more loyally by his side than his good wife.
多年来她辛苦照料……
She has tended to him with...
用始终如一的奉献精神
unfailing devotion,
爱 与尊敬
love, and honor.
为此 我对她心怀感激……
And for that, she has my gratitude...
和歉意
and my apology.
你的宽厚让我动容 公主
Your graciousness moves me deeply, Princess.
我们都是母亲……
We are both mothers...
都深爱着自己的孩子
and we love our children.
即使有时不愿承认 但我们其实有很多共同点
We have more in common than we sometimes allow.
我敬你和你的家族
I raise my cup to you and to your house.
你会是个好女王
You will make a fine queen.
我……
I...
我为你即将忍受的失望而感到遗憾
I regret the disappointment you are soon to suffer.
但如果你想感受一下真正的满足
But if you ever wish to know what it is to be well satisfied,
我乐意随时效劳
all you have to do is ask.
小杰
Jace.
敬伊耿和伊蒙德王子
To Prince Aegon and Prince Aemond.
虽然我们多年未见
We have not seen each other in years,
但年少时一起成长的时光我记忆犹新
but I have fond memories of our shared youth.
作为男人 希望我们可以既是朋友 又是同盟
And as men, I hope we may yet be friends and allies.
愿你和你的家庭健康常在 亲爱的舅舅们
To you and your family's good health, dear uncles.
也敬你
To you as well.
且牢记 木板底 凶兽起
Beware the beast beneath the boards.
干得好 孩子
Well done, my boy.
我想敬贝妮拉和雷妮亚
I would like to toast to Baela and Rhaena.
她们即将走入婚姻
They'll be married soon.
其实没那么糟 大多数时间他只是无视你而已……
It isn't so bad. Mostly he just ignores you...
喝醉的时候例外
except sometimes when he's drunk.
- 挺好 - 来点音乐吧
-Good. -Let us have some music.
不好意思
Excuse me.
护卫
Guards.
请坐
Please, sit down.
最后的致敬
Final tribute.
愿我的外甥们身体健康
To the health of my nephews:
小杰
Jace...
小路
Luke...
和乔佛里
and Joffrey.
愿他们每一位都英俊 智慧……
Each of them handsome, wise...
- 如斯强壮 - 伊蒙德
-strong. -Aemond.
来……
Come...
让我们干杯 为三个……
let us drain our cups to these three...
- 如斯强壮的男孩们 - 你敢再说一次
-Strong boys. -I dare you to say that again.
怎么了？不过是一句恭维罢了
Why? 'Twas only a compliment.
你觉得自己不够壮吗？
Do you not think yourself Strong?
- 小杰！- 够了！
-Jace! -That is enough!
你干嘛当着这么多人的面说这些？
Why would you say such a thing before these people?
我只是表达一下对家族的自豪罢了 母亲
I was merely expressing how proud I am of my family, Mother.
但好像我的外甥们对自己的家族没有那么多自豪感啊
Mm, though it seems my nephews aren't quite as proud of theirs.
等等 站住
Wait, wait!
回你们房间去 所有人 立刻
Go to your quarters. All of you go, now.
雷妮拉
Rhaenyra.
我觉得 我们最好还是先回龙石岛吧
It's best, I think, if we go back to Dragonstone.
你才刚来不久
You've only just arrived.
让我送孩子们回去
Let me see the children home.
我会……
I'll...
骑着龙再回来
return on dragonback.
陛下和我都希望如此
The King and I would both like that.
梅莎丽亚
“白蛆” “小梅夫人”
看样子今天的城堡之夜挺难熬啊
It's been quite a night at the castle, it seems
是的 夫人
Yes, my lady.
来 来
Come on, come on.
够了
That's it.
噢...
Oh...
好了
Well done.
- 抱歉 - 嘘
-I'm sorry. -Shh.
- 抱歉 - 嘘 嘘
-I'm sorry. -Shh, shh, shh.
你想知道……
But you wanted to know...
我是否相信
if I believe it to be true.
相信什么 陛下？
Believe what to be true, my King?
你不记得了吗？
Don't you remember?
伊耿……
Aegon...
我们的儿子？
Our son?
他的梦
His Dream.
冰与火……之歌——
The Song of Ice... and Fi--
是真的
It is true.
他于北方所见
What he saw in the North.
预言中的王子
The Prince That Was Promised.
我听不懂 韦赛里斯
I don't understand, Viserys.
那个王子
The Prince.
伊耿王子？
Prince Aegon?
将联合王国上下
To unite the realm
抵御寒冷……与长夜
against the cold... and the dark.
是你啊
It is you.
你就是那个人
You are the one.
你一定要做到
You must do this.
我明白了 陛下
I understand, my King.
够了
No more.
吾爱
My love.